all right it's April 4th 2024 this is an
update from the active infer ants
project where we're applying active
inference models to ants in
2021 working with other authors we
published an initial python code model
ant simulation with Niche modification
and forging with the single phermone
code was written initially by Alec in
that case adapting it from a previous
publication with axle at all that was
looking at cultural patterns of iates
and with other nestmates in the
subsequent years we continued to work on
and explore these different ideas
related to social physiology cyber
physical systems multiscale planning and
behavior and ant colonies and so on and
today I wanted to bundle together a
couple of updates related to the project
as there's just a great Confluence of
factors ranging from the RX and fur
team's live stream on building a drone
earlier today to just the inspiring work
in the RX andur project at the instit
and Holly's encouragement to look into
rust so the big announcement SLT
takeaway over at active inference
Institute GitHub slactive infer ant
let's start from scratch and multiple
places and converge and diverge and have
fun with ants and active inference and
for the rest of this video I'm going to
start zoomed in in the first section
talking a little bit methodologically
about how I used cursor. sh to translate
RX and F Julia code and pmdp python code
into new rust code and publish that open
source using a method with cursor that
pulls in GitHub repos and then we'll
zoom out a little bit and look at how
this draft SL sketch of the active
inference package is laid out and what
was retained through iterating locally
on my side and as mentioned before I
expect that we'll start from multiple
places and multiple step by steps so I
encourage that people get involved this
fun project and today I'll just show a
little bit that might spark some
thoughts and uh let's just see how to
also use these tools in a cool way so
I'm starting in folder _ other with the
Clone GitHub users python script this
script does work not all the scripts
work and the payload of this script is
that for whichever GitHub usernames are
provided it downloads all of the open
repos that that user has into a folder
called repo so here I've only left
selected bias lab which is the
developers of RX andur Julia and infer
actively which is the hosting group of
pmdp however I also curated some lists
of a bunch of other active inference
usernames and also some other things
that are fun to bring in like bringing
in energetics and quadres tetrahedral
coordination geometries as well as a lot
of ants and bioinformatics and also the
exciting development in multi-agent
Frameworks many could be added to all
these lists but just to kind of show the
minimal example what the current status
of the repo does is it clones in the
repos of bias lab and infer actively and
puts it into other then by going to the
gear on the top right of cursor
and then features resync
index cursor re indexes all of the code
which helps it for when you do the AI
chat you can do control enter and chat
with the code base so that is a super
helpful feature as is selecting text and
control K or doing control shift L to
move something over into the side window
so all these are methods that I'm sure
other people also have things that are
exciting for them and there's probably
many more improvements and meta
improvements to come but this clone
GitHub user script allowed me to bring
in exactly the genres and the repos one
by one in the repo script or in a batch
download with the
users and then cursor enabled me to chat
with the codebase to explain it better
and also to ask now write a pmdp styled
script for this situation so um two ways
in which I use that first I'll go
through the rust read me and then some
of the rust translations from the PDP
and RX and fer and then we'll return to
how the ants looked in the second
section so this is in the systems design
section of the repo because it's very
preliminary the goals of today's work
essentially where to use language models
and code and document methods to
translate and transform some open source
Python and Julia active inference code
into open source rust active inference
code to develop a noisy non-expert draft
sketch of an active inference ant colony
boldy scale simulation in Rust language
in order to learn highlight and explore
the unique performance and security
features of rust language for beginners
such as myself and to provide an initial
basis for further open source
development at the intersection of
active inference rust and ants so I used
cursor
0.331 with the GPT form model I use the
Clone GitHub user script to bring in as
many repos as possible related to active
inference or just a few resync the index
in cursor copied over from the rest of
the script some of the Python files and
renamed them to be rust files and then
here's some of the prompts that I used
in the side chat and in the control K
chat popup to help transform and iterate
on improve the code so these were just a
few of the prompts that
helped where it got me was some Rust
looking PDP style ants that I copied
over and multiple separate attempts to
write rust looking code not all of it
was tested and a lot of it is still
schematic but it's outlining at least an
approach that with a rust expert in the
loop I think we could have a great time
with the generalized multiscale modeling
of
things thing
class and this rust things starts in the
kind of agent-based approach along the
lines of the AOS active entity ontology
for Science and then I also tried
several other features based upon the
code models know of rust so rust meta
has some simulation
environment aspects rust system check
prints a lot of information about the
computer rust meta
configs has different kinds of
affordances for the then configuration
file which sets a bunch of the
parameters which are used later and then
in the rust worlds folder under config
this is even more speculative
so here we have cognitive security
classes in
Rust security classes in Rust and
porting over from 4D Solutions quadres
tetrahedral coordinates and Tetra
volumes those were both translated from
python so this just shows that by
bringing in repos related to active
inference we can transfer the semantics
of examples and hopefully there will be
a growing library of open- source
examples in all these different
languages and transfer and interpolate
within and outside of those bounds to
translate code and to get somewhere fast
with natural conversation which is super
exciting so now pulling back a little
bit folder zero in the
repo has some system specifications that
were also iteratively written with
language models and my put and then the
folders are as follows nine other has
some scripts related to cloning in repos
six API is for API calls which is also
just a kind of broadly outlined set of
methods most of the simulating and
preparing and all of the operating is in
the scripts 1 through five so in one
there's prepare so this has all of the
agent-based definitions including pmdp
ants that are defined and the general
and the config set different configs
most of these variables are not called
however it's fun to explore and just
build these hypothetical meta
configuration files and then in the
general preparation we have some scripts
pointing towards aspects of cognitive
security the course ordinates the IVM
and the XYZ coordinates being able to
flip between the coordination systems
implementing some cryptographic
metaphysical systems
nesting networking Network science
different physics including the
metaphysics and the cognitive physics
and then also for a little comedic
relief the Salt Fat acid heat simulator
in pmdp format so prepare gets all of
the configurations ready for assembling
the different things operate has a plan
render and execute three-step process
with a situational ant awareness
Observer role that actually
prepares plans out and then executes
computationally the
simulation measure has a set of scripts
and methods related to specif ifying how
you want to measure in a Quantum
cognitive frame and then how you're
going to summarize categorize and apply
statistics to the
measurements report is currently just
for this release the specify report
methods that detail how reporting is
going to occur and then the
specifications for followup which are
the implications of the report so that's
just one top level folder scheme for
multi-layer simulations like the active
inference package has to be and I look
forward to hearing about some radically
alternative starting points that we can
also have in our Colony so hope this is
at least interesting to some of you I
encourage people with some or a lot or
in between amount of familiarity with
active inference and ants and all these
different topics to come get involved
and come to our weekly RX and fur
meetings on Thursday join The Institute
Discord or email blanket active
inference do Institute or get in touch
another way because this is going to be
a fun project and really looking forward
to seeing how we can all start over and
collaborate on this further all
right